Guide to the Frederick George Marcham papers, 1925-1993.
Marcham, Frederick George papers, 1925-1993.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Frederick George Marcham papers, 1925-1993.
14-17-603
Frederick George Marcham, 1898-
9.4 cubic ft.
Correspondence, minutes, manuscripts, articles, course outlines, notebooks, files, an audiotape, passports, a diploma, account books, legal papers, and other materials.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Papers related to Marcham's work as Professor of English History at Cornell University.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Professor of English history, Cornell University.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Largely correspondence containing recommendations for former students and requests for such. Other letters deal with university affairs, publication of Marcham's books by MacMillan and Harper's, requests by publishing houses and scholarly journals for reader reports, and reports from students on their research progress. Includes some minutes of history department meetings, manuscripts of speeches and reports by Marcham and others, articles by Marcham on athletics, course outlines and notebooks, papers relating to history workshops offered at Cornell, items pertaining to the British Businessmen's Course (1948). Includes files pertaining to a program financed by the General Education Board intended to improve the level of teaching history in high schools, ca. 1943-1944, and files relating to a History Dept. program concerning teaching critical thinking, ca. 1940-1944. Also, drafts and working papers of his projected history of Cornell; "Essays on Oliver Cromwell" prepared by John Marcham; a tape recording of Marcham's memorial service. Also, passports, a diploma, account books, and legal papers.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Marcham, Frederick George, 1898-1992; Oliver Cromwell.; Cornell University--Faculty.; Cornell University--Students.; Cornell University--History.; Cornell University.; Harper & Row, Publishers.; Macmillan & Company.; University of Iowa.College of Education.
Subjects:
College students.; Education, Secondary.; College teachers.
Form and Genre Terms:
Notebooks.; Speeches.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
Boxes 7-11, and 18: access restricted to permission of donor.
RELATED MATERIALS
Includes collection 14-17-1489
CONTAINER LIST
- World War II newsletters and correspondence (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
- Correspondence, etc., 1930-1975
  - 1930 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 1944 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Case of D.B. Johnstone-Wallace, 1935-1949 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Faculty Committee 1948 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "Proposed Faculty Bill of Rights" (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 1949 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 1950-1952 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - 1953 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - 1954 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - 1955 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - 1956 (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
  - Jan.-May 1957 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - June-Dec. 1957 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Jan.-May 1958 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - June-Dec. 1958 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Jan.-June 1959 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - July-Dec. 1959 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Jan.-June 1960 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - July-Sept. 1960 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Oct.-Dec. 1960 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Jan.-Feb. 1961 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Mar.-June 1961 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - July-Dec. 1961 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Jan.-Apr. 1962 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - May-Dec. 1962 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Jan.-Apr. 1963 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - May-Sept. 1963 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Oct.-Dec. 1963 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Jan.-Apr. 1964 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - May-Aug. 1964 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Sept.-Dec. 1964, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Jan.-Apr. 1965 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - May-Oct. 1965 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Nov.-Dec. 1965 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Keast Report, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Jan.-Mar. 1966 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Apr.-June 1966 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - July-Aug. 1966 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Sept.-Oct. 1966 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Nov.-Dec. 1966 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Jan.-Apr. 1967 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - May-Aug. 1967 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Sept.-Dec. 1967 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Western Civilization, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Jan.-Feb. 1968 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Mar.-June 1968 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - July-Oct. 1968 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Nov.-Dec. 1968 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Jan.-Apr. 1969 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - May-Aug. 1969 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Ad Hoc Judiciary Committee, Aug. 1969 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Sept.-Oct. 1969 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Nov.-Dec. 1969 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Jan.-Apr. 1970 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - May-Aug. 1970 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Sept.-Dec. 1970 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Jan.-June 1971 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - July-Dec. 1971 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Jan.-June 1972 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - July-Dec. 1972 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Jan.-June 1973 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - July-Dec. 1973 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - History Dept., Sept.-Oct. 1973 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Jan.-June 1974 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - July-Dec. 1974 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Alumni University 1974 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - 1975 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Letters from Charles S. Stonocle (?) (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - undated and fragments (Box 3, Folder 35)
- Projects, etc., 1941-1971
  - Critical Thinking Project, 1941-1947
    - Critical Thinking Project (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Negotiations (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Ithaca Correspondence (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Supervision Schedules (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - 1941-1942 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Expense Accounts (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - School Correspondence (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Environmental Set-up (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Teaching Critical Thinking (Box 4, Folder 10-11)
    - Report 1940-1941 Dunn (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Test Data (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Grade 7 (Box 4, Folder 14-16)
    - Grade 8 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Grade 9 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Grade 10 (Box 4, Folder 19-20)
    - Grade 11 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Typescripts of Documents (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Workshop on Latin America, the Far East and the British Commonwealth, 1942-1946
    - Workshop on Latin America, the Far East and the British Commonwealth of Nations, 1942-1946 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Workshop Financial Statements (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Workshop (correspondence), 1944-1945 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - 1945 Workshop (inquiries and orders) (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - British Commonwealth (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Latin America (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - The Far East (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Cornell University Curriculum Series in World History, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - British Businessmen's Course, 1948
    - British Businessmen's Course, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 32-33)
    - Drafts (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Course Outlines (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Writings
    - "Essays on Oliver Cromwell" prepared by John Marcham, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Letters of an English Physician in the early Seventeenth Century", by F. G. Marcham, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Six short essays presenting my thoughts on myself as a member of my community" by F. G. Marcham, 1960, 1969, 1975, 1984, 1986, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Reports, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 36-37)
    - Reports, speeches, etc., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Speech for Mr. and Mrs. Cyrus Eaton re: Goldwin Smith, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Photographs
    - Photographs (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Oversize photograph of Prof. Marcham with group of British businessmen, 1948 (Mapcase-folder 1)
  - Articles
    - Athletics Articles (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - Toward an Ivy Group Handbook for Intercollegiate Athletics, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Clippings
    - Miscellaneous clippings (Box 4, Folder 43)
- History Course Notebooks
  - History Course Notebooks (Box 5)
  - History Course Notebooks (Box 6)
- Notebooks and Related Papers
  - Notebooks and Related Papers (Box 7)
  - Notebooks and Related Papers (Box 8)
  - Notebooks and Related Papers (Box 9)
  - Notebooks and Related Papers (Box 10)
  - Notebooks and Related Papers (Box 11)
- Unprocessed Material
  - Unprocessed Material (Box 12)
  - Unprocessed Material (Box 13)
  - Unprocessed Material (Box 14)
  - Unprocessed Material (Box 15)
  - Unprocessed Material (Box 16)
  - Unprocessed Material (Box 17)
  - Unprocessed Material (Box 18)
  - Unprocessed Material (Box 19)